Guide to the Jay Katz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jay Katz papers
1947-2003
MS 1958
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7
(18 boxes)
The collection comprises the papers of medical doctor, Yale Law School professor, and bioethicist Jay Katz. The papers document Katz's significant contributions to the field of bioethics, through both his teaching and scholarship, and through his public service and advocacy as a member of two federal committees charged to investigate human medical experiments. The papers consist of correspondence; files pertaining to Katz's work as a member of the Tuskegee Syphilis Ad Hoc Advisory Panel and the Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments; drafts of speeches delivered by Katz; subject files; files pertaining to classes taught by Katz as a professor at Yale Law School; and drafts of articles and books written by Katz.
Katz, Jay, 1922-2008
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises the papers of medical doctor, Yale Law School professor, and bioethicist Jay Katz. The papers document Katz's significant contributions to the field of bioethics, through both his teaching and scholarship, and through his public service and advocacy as a member of two federal committees charged to investigate human medical experiments. The papers consist of correspondence; files pertaining to Katz's work as a member of the Tuskegee Syphilis Ad Hoc Advisory Panel and the Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments; drafts of speeches delivered by Katz; subject files; files pertaining to classes taught by Katz as a professor at Yale Law School; and drafts of articles and books written by Katz.
Biographical / Historical
Jacob "Jay" Katz was born on October 20, 1922, in Zwickau, Germany, where his father was a business owner. When Adolph Hitler and the Nazi Party came to power in 1933, Katz's family's German citizenship was revoked. His father arranged for him to obtain a Czech passport, and at age sixteen, Katz traveled alone to Prague, and ultimately to the United States by way of Italy and Great Britain. The rest of his family joined him in the United States in 1940.
Katz graduated from the University of Vermont in 1944, and in 1949 he earned his medical degree from Harvard Medical School. Following his education, Dr. Katz completed his internship and residency in New York City, and then enlisted in the United States Air Force, serving as a First Lieutenant and Captain at the Maxwell Air Force Base hospital in Montgomery, Alabama.
Katz's career at Yale University began in 1953 when he was appointed Chief Resident at the Yale School of Medicine's outpatient clinic. He began teaching psychiatry at Yale in 1955, and in 1958 was named Assistant Professor of Psychiatry and Law at Yale. Dr. Katz's work in the areas of medical law and bioethics began when he served on a committee that drafted the Connecticut law that established the terms of patient privilege for psychotherapists and their patients in 1961. This law served as a model for the Federal Rules of Evidence, which are enforced across the United States.
In 1972, Katz was named to serve on a federal committee charged to investigate the Tuskegee Syphilis Experiment, begun in 1932 to study the progression and effects of untreated syphilis in about 400 impoverished African-American men from rural Alabama. The infected men were never told that they had syphilis, and were never treated for it, though they were compensated for their participation in the study with free health care, meals, and burial insurance. The committee concluded that the experiment was unethical, that the participants should have been treated for their infections, and called for greater governmental oversight and protection of subjects in medical studies.
In 1994, Katz was appointed to serve on the Advisory Committee on Human Radiation Experiments, charged by President Bill Clinton to investigate 30 experiments in which individuals were unknowingly exposed to radiation. Katz was active on a number of other bioethics issues, as an outspoken proponent of the concept of informed consent, and as an opponent of the use of data gathered during Nazi medical experiments.
Katz was the prolific author of six books and numerous articles, and wrote extensively on topics related to the relationship between medicine, ethics, and law. He died on November 17, 2008, at the age of eighty-six at his home in New Haven, Connecticut.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged into seven series: I. Correspondence, 1961-2003. II. Federal investigation files, 1931-1997. III. Speeches, 1961-1997. IV. Subject files, 1959-1999. V. Teaching files, 1961-2001. VI. Writings, 1972-1997. VII. Electronic files, 1985-1990.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marilyn Katz, 2010.
Bioethics; United States. Advisory Committee on Human Radiation Experiments; United States. Tuskegee Syphilis Study Ad Hoc Advisory Panel
- Correspondence, 1961-2003; Series I (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Arrangement
  Materials arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises a small assortment of both incoming and outgoing correspondence that primarily concerns Katz's scholarship, writings, and speaking engagements. It includes extensive correspondence from the 1960s and 1970s with Anna Freud, a notable figure in the field of child psychology and the daughter of Sigmund Freud. Anna Freud was a visiting lecturer at Yale Law School during the period documented in the correspondence.
  - General, 1961-2003 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Freud, Anna, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Federal investigation files, 1939-1997; Series II
  This series comprises Katz's papers from his service on the Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments and the Tuskegee Syphilis Ad Hoc Advisory Panel. The papers from the Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments consist of memoranda and subject files. The majority of the memoranda were written and distributed to Katz and other members of the Advisory Committee by the committee's staff or in some cases, fellow committee members. The memos provide valuable insight into the committee's investigative process, particularly the ethical framework that it developed through which to analyze the experiments in question. The memos also richly document the drafting of the committee's final report, and include drafts and revisions of sections of the report, and comments on the drafts made by committee members. The remainder of the memoranda concern many of the radiation experiments that the committee investigated, including the nuclear weapons tests at the Marshall Islands during the 1940s and 1950s; the Nuclear Energy for the Propulsion of Aircraft (NEPA) project; human plutonium injection experiments at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory during the 1940s; and Operation Paperclip, which involved the recruitment of German scientists to work for the U.S. government following World War II. Many of these memos are accompanied by copies of relevant historical documents, and/or summary reports compiled by committee staff members.
  The subject files from the Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments consist mostly of copies of historical documents concerning the radiation experiments investigated by the committee. These include declassified government documents, meeting minutes, interview transcriptions, and reports. The subject files provide further documentation of the committee's investigation of the NEPA project and the Marshall Islands nuclear weapons tests, and also document investigations into other radiation experiments, including the Operation Teapot nuclear weapons tests of 1955; and medical radiation experiments performed on subjects at the Arctic Aeromedical Laboratory in Alaska, at the Medical College of Virginia, and at Vanderbilt University during the 1940s and 1950s.
  The papers from Katz's tenure on the Tuskegee Syphilis Study Ad Hoc Advisory Panel consist of correspondence, copies of historical documents related to the experiment, articles and press clippings documenting the panel's work, and administrative documents pertaining to the panel's investigation. The correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing correspondence, primarily between Katz and other members of the panel. The historical documents consist mostly of copies of correspondence between doctors who participated in the Tuskegee Syphilis Study, as well as copies of periodic reports on the status of the experiment. These materials span the entire course of the experiment, from the 1930s to the early 1970s, with the bulk of the historical documents dating from the 1930s. Administrative records of the advisory panel include a copy of its final report, copies of internal memos, and transcriptions of the proceedings of the panel's meetings.
  - Advisory Committee on Radiation Experiments, 1943-1995, bulk 1994-1995; 1994-1995
    - Memoranda
      - General, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
      - Atomic veterans, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Committee on Medical Science, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Commonwealth of Massachusetts report on human subject research, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Contemporary environmental oversight on human radiation experiments, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Documentation on worker studies at Los Alamos and Oak Ridge National Laboratories, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Drafting of final report, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4-8)
      - Ethics, current policies and procedures, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Ethics data collection follow-up, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Ethics follow-up, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Experiments on military personnel, miscellaneous materials, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Experimentation on prisoners, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Hamilton, Joseph, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Human experimentation to develop a nuclear-powered airplane, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Marshall Islands, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Nuclear Energy for the Propulsion of Aircraft (NEPA), total body irradiation (TBI), psychological testing, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Oak Ridge National Laboratory, human experiments, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Post-World War II recruitment of German scientists (Project Paperclip), 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Progress report on collection of agency ethical standards on human experimentation, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Recently proposed legislation regarding human radiation experiments, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Shields, Warren, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Wilson memorandum, 1953, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Working list of acronyms, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Subject files, 1943-1995
      - General, 1949-1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Alaska, human experiments during the 1950s, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Cesium studies, 1957-1976 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Committee roster, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Department of the Army, memorandum on the use of volunteers in research, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Department of Defense, Committee on Medical Sciences, meeting transcripts, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Department of Defense, Committee on Medical Sciences, meeting transcripts, 1949-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Department of Energy regulations, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Drafts, final report fragment, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Drafts, memos on history of Department of Defense ethics policies, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Drafts, part 1, chapter 3, Cold War ethics policy, 1994-1995 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Glenn, John, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Greaves, F. C., Resume of meeting with the Atomic Energy Commission, Advisory Board of the Division of Biology and Medicine, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - "History of the Regulation of Human Experimentation", 1994 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Katz, Jay, statement regarding the committee's final report, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Lederer, Susan, background materials for committee briefing on human experimentation, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Marshall Islands, 1953-1994 (Box 6, Folder 5-8)
      - Medical College of Virginia, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - National security documents, 1943-1957 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Nuclear Energy for the Propulsion of Aircraft (NEPA), Advisory Committee on Radiation Tolerance of Military Personnel, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Nuclear Energy for the Propulsion of Aircraft (NEPA), Executive Panel, Medical Advisory Committee meeting minutes, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Operation Teapot, research report, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Radiation exposure cases, 1985-1987 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Randall, Carey, transcript of conversation, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Secretary of the Navy, report, "Unauthorized Medical Experimentation on Service Personnel", 1943 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - United States Atomic Energy Commission, declassified documents, 1943-1955 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
      - University of Cincinnati, College of Medicine, report, "Metabolic Changes in Humans Following Total Body Irradiation", 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Vanderbilt University, radioactive iron experiments on women in the 1940s, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Tuskegee Syphilis Study Ad Hoc Advisory Panel, 1931-1997; 1972-1973
    - Agendas, orientation session, 1972 September 14 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Articles and reports on the Tuskeegee Syphilis Study, 1931-1955, 1974-1997 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Charter, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1972-1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Final report, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Final report on charge I-A, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Final report of the National Medical Association, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Finding aids to historical documents and collections, 1973, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Historical documents, 1930-1959, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Hodge, Harold, interview, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Internal communication, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
    - Laurie, Eunice, interview, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Meeting, transcript of proceedings, 1972 September 27 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Meeting, transcript of proceedings, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
    - Press clippings, 1972-1993 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Subject files, 1901-1996 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
- Speeches, 1961-1997; Series III
  Materials arranged chronologically.
  This series consists of copies of speeches delivered by Katz that richly reflect his scholarship and activism in the field of bioethics. Materials in the series date from the early 1960s through the late 1990s, spanning almost the entirety of Katz's career. Included are many speeches on the topic of informed consent of medical patients, as well as many that concern his work in the area of human medical experimentation. In many instances, the city and/or venue in which a speech was delivered are specified.
  - "A Psychoanalyst at the Law School," New Haven (CT), 1961 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Some Comments on the Role of Lawyers and Psychiatrists in Marital Disruptions", 1962 November (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Freedom and Medical Control of Society", 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - "Ethical Aspects of Experimentation on Human Subjects", 1966 December 5 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Some Questions to Psychoanalysis From Law About Adoption", 1966 December 17 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - "The Influence of Human Experimentation on the Practice of Medicine", 1967 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Discussion of 'Confidentiality in the Community Mental Health Center'", 1968 January 31 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - "Discussion of Paper on Homosexuality and the Law", 1968 May 14 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - "The Psychiatrist in Court: Expert or Advocate?", 1970 January 12 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - "The Decision for Abortion: Public or Private?", 1972 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Congressional testimony, 1973 June 30 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - "The Tuskegee Syphilis Study: Forty Years of Experimentation with Human Beings", 1973 September (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - "On Informed Consent", 1973 September (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - "Human Rights and Human Experimentation", 1973 November (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - "Caring for Research: Has Medical Education Failed?", 1974 May (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - "Informed Consent," Pittsburgh (PA), 1974 May (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - "Address to Yale Medical Staff", 1974 December 10 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - "Who's Afraid of Informed Consent?", 1974 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - "Research with Prisoners: The Need for Reform", 1975 January 31 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - "Individual Risks vs. Societal Benefits - How are the Risks Distributed? - The Poor", 1975 February (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Untitled remarks on Dr. Duff, 1975 May 20 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - "Discussion at Yale Medical Grand Rounds", 1975 June 19 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - "On Professional Responsibility," San Diego (CA), 1975 July 14 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - "Informed Consent: A Fairytale?" University of Pittsburgh, [1975], 1977 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - "Discussion of 'The Ethics of Sex Therapy' by Fritz Redlich," St. Louis (MO), 1976 January 23 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - "Discussion of Papers on Patient Rights vs. Therapeutic Needs", 1976 January 23 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - "On Informed Consent," Yale Medical School Alumni Panel, 1976 June (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - "Informed Consent? Can Physicians Even Tell, and Patients Know, the Truth?", 1978 (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - "Disclosure and Consent: In Search of their Roots", 1980 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Untitled presentation at a bioethics conference, 1980 October (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - "Acknowledging Uncertainty: Its Impact on Physicians and Patients", 1981 April 16 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - "Informed Consent: Medicine's Vision", 1982 March (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - "The Dying Patient: Medicine's Ultimate Responsibility," Yale Medical School, 1982 May (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - "The Fear of Informed Consent", 1982 October 25 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - "Obstacles to Informed Consent", 1983 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - "When Should Patients' Choices Not Be Respected?", 1983 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - "Can Principles Survive in Situations of Critical Care?", 1983 March 17 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Comments," Holocaust conference, Yale University, 1983 November 5 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - "Discussion of the Case of Mrs. M.B.", 1986 January 21 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - "The Social and Medical Origins of the PHS Directive on Human Studies", 1986 February 6 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - "Discussion of the Case of Mrs. A and Mrs. B.", 1986 May 3 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - "The Regulation of Human Experimentation in the U.S.: A Personal Odyssey," Chicago (IL), 1986 May 15 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - "Medical Malpractice: A Case Study in Decision-Making," Yale Medical School, 1986 December 6 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - "What Comes Under the Rubric of a Law and Medicine Course?", 1987 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - "Informed Consent and the New Reproductive Technologies: Who Speaks for the Child?", 1987 May 30 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - "Duty and Caring", 1987 October 30 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - "Benefiting from Evil: The Concentration Camp Experiments", 1988 July 22 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - "Opening Remarks: Task Force on Psychiatric Treatment Records in Child Custody Disputes", 1988 August 25 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - "Discussions of Edgar L. Lipton Paper on 'Considerations Concerning Discussions and Publications of Case Histories'", 1988 December 17 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - "Can a Seriously Ill Patient Refuse Treatment?", 1989 February (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - "The Holocaust and Biomedical Ethics: The Use of Nazi Data," New Haven (CT), 1989 November 17 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - "Remarks Following Dean Guido Calabresi's Announcement of the Elizabeth K. Dollard Professorship", 1990 October 12 (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - "The Fallacy of the Impartial Expert Revisited", 1991 October 19 (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - "Can Consent Even Be Informed?", 1991 November 15 (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - "Duty and Caring in the Age of Medical Science and Informed Consent", 1991 September 26 (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - "Protecting Human Subjects: Unfulfilled Promises," Boston, MA, 1991 November 2 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - "Can Consent Ever Be Informed?", 1991 December 5 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - "Human Experimentation and Human Rights", 1992 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - "'What I May See or Hear...I Will Keep to Myself:' The Anne Sexton Tapes", 1992 May 5 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "Discovering the Patient," Commencement Address, Eastern Virginia Medical School, 1992 May 16 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "The Birth of Bioethics," Seattle, WA, 1992 September 24 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - "Informed Consent: Must it Remain a Fairy Tale?", 1993 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - "Human Experimentation and Human Rights," Philadelphia (PA), 1994 May 16 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - "Testimony Before the Subcommittee on Regulation, Business Opportunities, and Technology", 1994 May 23 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - "Discovering the Patient", 1994 May 28 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - "Human Rights and Human Experimentation," Harvard Medical School, 1994 November 10 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - "Ethics in Neurobiological Research with Human Subjects", 1995 January (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - "Reflections on the Doctors' Trial," Yale Hillel, 1996 September 19 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - "Human Sacrifice and Human Experimentation: Reflections at Nuremberg", 1996 October 27 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - "Human Subjects Protection: What Have We Learned From Nuremberg?", 1996 November 22 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - "The Doctors' Trial: What Have We Learned?", 1996 December 10 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - "The Nazi Doctors' Trial: What Have We Learned?", 1997 May 23 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - "The Nazi Doctors' Trial: What Have We Learned?", 1977 June 11 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - "Reflections on Informed Consent: 40 Years After its Birth", 1997 October 15 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - "Benefiting from Evil", Undated (Box 13, Folder 20)
  - "Conflict and Trust", Undated (Box 13, Folder 21)
  - "Contribution of the Tuskegee Study to Scientific Knowledge", Undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
  - "Decision-Making Between Doctors and Patients", Undated (Box 13, Folder 23)
  - "Human Experimentation" (outline), Undated (Box 13, Folder 24)
  - "Opening Remarks at a Faculty Meeting in Memory of Bob Cover", Undated (Box 13, Folder 25)
  - "Peter Browning Hoffman", Undated (Box 13, Folder 26)
  - "The Teaching of 'Ethics and the Life Sciences'", Undated (Box 13, Folder 27)
  - "The Tuskegee Syphilis Study: Its Implications for the Future Regulation of Human Research", Undated (Box 13, Folder 28)
  - Remarks on Bruce Ennis, Undated (Box 13, Folder 29)
- Subject files, 1959-1999; Series IV
  This series consists of an assortment of files related to Jay Katz's research interests and scholarship. It includes several folders containing research materials on the case of Mary Northern, a Tennessee resident who in the 1970s was the focus of a famous medical ethics case concerning the concept of informed consent.
  - Ethics in neurobiological research with human subjects conference, 1995 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Family law
    - Committee on the Child and the Law, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Papers on family law and divorce, 1959-1961 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - German articles, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - "Internal Review Boards Through the Looking Glass" conference agenda, 1999 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Model rules of conduct for lawyers, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Northern, Mary
    - Chancery Court Documents, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1980-1982 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Court of Appeals, transcript of proceedings, 1978 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Harvard Business School study, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Research materials, 1978-1981 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Tennessee Court of Appeals, application for stay of mandate, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Sexton, Anne, biography controversy, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 13)